[Music]
it's the real news on their nature in a
landmark case the architect of the CIA's
torture program have reached a
settlement with its victim the
psychologists James Mitchell and Bruce
Jessen have agreed to undisclosed terms
with two victims in the families of a
third it's the first time top officials
in the CIA torture program are being
held at least somewhat to account
joining me is someone who has helped
make this happen John Kerry ah who is a
former CIA analyst who exposed the
torture book and is the only official
jail in connection with it John welcome
thanks for having me I should say you
were the only official who was jailed
with it because you're out of jail now
and we're very happy to speak to you
because you have a real connection with
this case your response to the seller I
know the ACLU is very happy and I know
that that one of the victims said he was
very happy and that he felt that justice
was served but I actually am
disappointed in this settlement for a
number of reasons first of all the
decision is sealed so we really don't
know if justice has been served we don't
know what the terms of the agreement are
we don't know if there is any kind of
deterrent that has been written been
written into to the decision so the fact
that it's not public it seems to me at
least in part defeats the purpose of the
second Mitchell and Jessen the two the
two CIA contractors psychologists who
were the the defendants in this case
were indemnified by the CIA in 2001 so
even though they were sued the CIA paid
for their attorneys the CIA is paying
for the settlement the CIA is paying for
everything and when I say the CIA
pegboard I mean that you and I are
paying for it the American taxpayers are
paying for it so there's no actual hurt
to Mitchell and Jessen and third you
know this
had it gone to trial would have exposed
CIA documents related to the torture
program that we otherwise will never
have access to and we're going to lose
that now
so whatever didn't come out with the
Senate torture report and could have
come out with this case will not come
out and we'll just never know what the
truth is behind this case you know a few
things let me start with who Mitchell
and Jessen are you talk about US
taxpayers paying their legal fees well
it wasn't just that right because before
that to the diners program Mitchell and
Jessen received millions of dollars to
get create the program he talked about
what they did and the techniques that
they came up with that these victims
were subjected to yeah Mitchell and
Jessen were psychologists in the
Department of the Air Force and they
reverse engineered the Air Force's sere
training program to to use offensively
against terrorism suspects and so this
became the torture program this became
the the ten techniques that were used
that the Bush White House
euphemistically called enhanced
interrogation techniques now in addition
to being paid of the standard you know
one thousand fifty dollars a day that
almost every CIA contractors pay
Mitchell and Jessen over the course of
several years were paid an additional 81
million dollars to come up with this
program and to then implement it now
what makes it even worse than just
coming up with the program is that they
went overseas to the secret prisons and
they were the ones who actually carried
out the torture there will be no
punishment for them for doing that right
and let's talk about these victims
Suleiman Salim Mohammed Ahmed been sued
and the family of full rocman rockman is
is now deceased let's talk about what
they went through I know that at least a
few of them Saleem and Sood I'm not
familiar with Rothman's case they were
held for years and ultimately world to
pose no threat at all as it
the case with so many of these victims
of us rendition and torture and imprison
that's right the two surviving victims
of the CIA's torture program were
tortured mercilessly and at least
because they had nothing to do with
terrorism they were scooped up in the
so-called fog of war they were sent to
Guantanamo before that they were sent to
secret prisons and they were they were
tortured it turns out they were the
wrong guys gule Rahman is a particularly
sad case gule Rahman was subjected to a
torture technique called the cold cell
in which he was changed to an eyebolt in
the ceiling like this he was stripped
naked he was his cell was chilled to 50
degrees Fahrenheit and then every hour a
CIA officer would enter the cell and
throw a bucket of ice water on him
Gold Rodman was killed with that
technique he didn't make it through the
night and died of hypothermia no one has
ever been brought to justice for
murdering goal rahman and certainly the
Justice Department never gave CIA
officers permission to to murder
detainees during the course of their
interrogations well Gul Rahman's torture
and death were overseen by Mitchell and
Jessen and again
there's no justice for bull Rockland
right so certainly Mitchell and Jessen
had a real reason to not want this case
to go to trial let me ask you those two
Falls of something you said before in
terms of documents that would have come
out in a court case not being able to
know is there not a second lawsuit that
the ACLU also filed against Mitchell and
Jessen and if that's still ongoing could
that not possibly shed the light that is
being foreclosed here yeah there's a
second case pending filed by the ACLU on
behalf of I believe I was the data now I
was a beta is is far more controversial
because he was sort of Mitchell and
Jessen guinea pig for this whole program
I'm sort of tied to Abu Zubaydah for
life I was responsible for his capture
when the CIA believed that I was a beta
with the number three in al-qaeda he was
never the number three in al-qaeda and
in fact he had never even joined
al-qaeda but the intelligence was faulty
well he was tortured
so lessly and he was the first one to
undergo this torture he has never faced
any kind of justice he's never met his
accusers in a court of law he's never
faced a jury of his peers and he's never
even been charged with a crime
so not only not only was he tortured but
he's been held indefinitely and had
literally no hope of release so I hope
that his case will eventually bring some
of these properties to life they're too
light rather now the problem with our
Savannah is that because he's so
controversial
and because he was the focus of the
Senate torture report I think the
chances are very good that the CIA will
invoke a national security defense and
ask the judge to dismiss this case with
prejudice before any testimony is heard
John just to flesh out your connection
with him that you mentioned if I recall
right you put him on the plane that took
him to where he was held and fortunately
yeah that's right I literally picked him
up along with three FBI agents he was on
a gurney we lifted him up and maneuvered
him into a secret CIA jet and strapped
him to the luggage rack at the back he
asked me to hold his hand he was crying
it was very upset and I and I told him a
number of times I'm the nicest guy
you're going to encounter in this
experience if I can give you any advice
it's that you have to cooperate and he
said you seem like a nice man but you're
the enemy and I'll never cooperate and I
wished him luck and I never saw him
again
so finally John I know you mentioned
that you're disappointed in this
settlement because it means that work
that these two are not going to be held
accountable in court but I'm wondering
if you as someone who exposed this
program if you can at least feel any
comfort that two of its victims and the
family of the third who died as you
explained to us are going to experience
some modicum of justice you know it I
would expect that the settlement is is
many millions of dollars I don't think
that that Salim would have even said
that justice had been served without a
provision of millions of dollars so
in and of itself is a great thing
another great thing is with this
Agreement the CIA has effectively
admitted that it had a torture program
not an enhanced interrogation technique
program not an interrogation program but
a torture program so at least we have
that and I hope that the organization
can learn from its past mistakes its
past atrocities and not ever carry
anything out like this again okay you
know what a quick follow-up something I
meant to ask you the CIA in some ways
did cooperate with the plaintiffs here
right and if that's a fair
characterization does that signal
perhaps that the CIA is businessing
itself from Mitchell and Jessen and
would be open to some form of future
accountability I think that's right and
and it's it's odd and it's almost
inexplicable but when the CIA announced
at the at the very end of the Obama
administration that it would not seek to
to have the case thrown out I thought
well we'll see if it lasts what the next
president with the next president here
we are with Donald Trump Donald Trump's
CIA did not seek to have the case thrown
out so I think that this was something
that the CIA decided to do at the top
most levels just to put it behind them
laughter but we'll have to leave it
there John Kiriakou
the CIA analysts who exposed the CIA
torture program went to jail for it John
thank you thanks for having me and thank
you for joining us on the room